[Music]
so
hello everybody good evening good day to
all of you welcome to the latest episode
of the ask abidjit show
i hope you're all doing
great um and let's see who all we have
with us and yes like yesterday today's
video is sponsored by the like button go
hit it and
help our sponsors
so we have with us krishna
raghav bihari gal
aman shivraj vinay
newaguna give you up
radhakrishnan
dj destruction
saket aman anway tukesh
kuldeep
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you great to see you
here rajat pranav aman
amar pranjal swapnil and everybody else
so today we're gonna talk about
geopolitics and history mostly um and
current affairs
uh
so let us begin with the questions and i
think we should begin with the question
that everybody is asked the most
the the question do you
which is of course this one
lots of people have asked about this so
i've taken one which represents all the
people who ask this question i got
dozens of
various versions of this question so the
question is very simple what is the
agnibat scheme it is by rajat is it a
good or a bad initiative by the
government why are so many people
protesting yes good question it's become
a big uh
well yeah
controversy for whatever reason so let
me share the screen and see uh and kind
of show what's going on
so people are people are saying it's a
bad scheme
various are retired personal etcetera
person army generals and so on so let me
give you just one example of that
so this is one example there are lots of
retired
army personnel who are saying similar
things so this is by a
lieutenant general vinod bhatia retired
and this gentleman says death knell for
the armed forces tod not tour of duty
not tested no pilot project straight
implementation will also lead to the
militarization of society nearly 75
youth uh year on year back rejected and
dejected without a job
semi trained in arms especially example
agreement it's not a good idea nobody
gains no one games and games
so there is one example and there are
lots of other examples lots of media
people lots of retired uh
army people and so on are criticizing
this uh i read some an article said that
this is like a kindergarten scheme for
the army is going to ruin the army blah
blah blah blah blah and on and on
so the impression that they are trying
to create
is that this is terrible for the armed
forces it's going to be the death knell
for the armed forces this is the end
destroyed the army is going to be
destroyed and so on how much of this is
true
they were saying similar things about
the farm laws and i supported the farm
loads and i got hundreds of comments
saying that abhijit you are wrong
you're mistaken you're stupid blah blah
blah fine okay you disagree and it's
fine it's fine with me i don't take it
personally now
so what are the characteristics of the
tour of duty the ognipath scheme uh it
is between the ages of 17 and half i
think end 22 or 23 or something this
year it's going to be extended up to a
couple of years of age maybe 24 or
something like that whatever it is so
this year is an exceptional year they're
going to extend it by two years the age
the upper age
but
going forward is going to be between
seven and a half 17 and a half years and
22. so if you are within that age range
you are eligible for this now it's a
four-year
tour of duty so you're not getting a
permanent job you're getting a four-year
commission
in those four years you will become a
proper soldier you'll be trained the
training is about six months then you go
on a tour of duty you serve in the armed
forces you get a salary of i don't know
30 40 000 a month something like that
yeah
and then after the end of four years
one-fourth of the people who came into
your batch will be retained the rest
will be released back into the civilian
population
what you will get if you are released is
you will get
about 12 lakh rupees that
that's
what the government will give you a lump
sum kind of thing right it's a 12 lakh
rupee corpus 11 point something nearly
12 lakh rupees and since you have served
in the armed forces for four years and
since there are there are there's almost
no expenditure the salary that you
acquired will also be saved so that's
roughly give it uh give or take 10 lakh
rupees
so once you're out
let's say you went in at the age of 12
of the the age of 18 and you're out at
the age of 22. at the age of 22 you will
get a lump sum 22 lakh rupee corpus
of money 22 lakh rupees at the age of 22
you have 22 lakh rupees in your bank
account how many 22 year olds
know what 22 lakh rupees looks like i
didn't know what 22 lakh rupees looked
like they have 22 i didn't know what 10
lakh rupees looked like at the age of
22. so you are getting a start in life
with 22 lakh rupees can you imagine that
is that a bad thing
and see it's like this not everybody is
cut out for the armed forces so
one-fourth will be retained those who
have performed really well and those who
have shown the inclination to stay
in for the long game the others they
will get all the skills all the training
the leadership training the the fitness
training various other mechanical and
technological training that you need in
the armed forces to be effective and
then you're out into the job market at
the age of 22 when everybody else
graduates and so on you already got some
training which will add to the credit
which will be like half of graduation
so whatever training you got in these
four years will those that will add that
will be recognized as credits towards a
degree so it will be like half your
degree is done right there in case you
want to go for a degree but most people
i would say would take this 22 lakh
rupees and start a business or start
something or so some people would want
to
go into the crpa for
whatever it is right something like that
so there are so many options open at the
age of 22 once you're out of it
now
and one of the uh
objections that people are raising
is that in six months you cannot train a
soldier in four years you will not be
trained sufficiently it is going to
reduce the army to a kindergarten
four years
that's all they're saying
i think everybody on this channel and
most people in india
have the highest regard
for the idf israeli defense force yes
do you know that in israel there is
compulsory conscription it's a
three-year tour of duty
in three years the train their personnel
their soldiers fully if they after this
three-year term they're back into the
civilian population
you think the israeli armed forces are
not sufficiently well trained is that
the impression that you get
no they are one of the best and most
professional armed forces in the world
and their training period their entire
tour period is three years
we are doing it for four years you think
we can't achieve the same level or
better level of proficiency and
competency and professionalism in a
four-year term
tour of duty what nonsense is this sort
of argument stupid argument in israel
you have three years similar similar
cases are there in the us in in south
korea
they also have similar things also
russia germany taiwan the uk all of
these countries have similar uh schemes
these they all have extremely well
trained armed forces
so this argument falls flat on its face
and these people who are making the
arguments that this is not tested
there's a death knell for armed forces
they seem to have some ulterior motives
all right i am not pointing figures at
any specific individual i'm not even
pointing fingers at the the person whose
tweet i showed i'm just saying in
general
there seems to be something going on
they are trying to misrepresent what is
happening
right now
the average age of the average indian
armed forces soldier
or officer or whatever the average age
of any any random person is about 32 to
33 years it's
rather old so by implementing the scheme
we're going to have a younger fitter and
more modern and more dynamic
corpus of soldiers
right
in the armed forces it's good we need
fresh intake we need
young blood in the armed forces younger
people stronger
stronger and fitter people right and a
more modern outlook that comes in from
the young people
teenagers and youngsters are very future
future oriented
mob they are very modernized modern
their orientation and attitude is very
modern much more than people who are
older
so it's a good thing
and not everybody wants a job for life
today the teenagers the youngsters they
want to explore different things but
they also want to contribute something
to their country and to the defense of
their country this is a scheme that is
perfect for that you know
and some people say that it's going to
destroy the culture of the armed forces
what stupid claim is that the culture
and the traditions of the armed forces
are passed on via the officers
and this agni veer agni pat scheme is
not for the intake of officers it is for
the intake of personnel who come below
the officer level so it's not going to
change anything about the culture of the
armed forces if the officers can do
their job then the culture is there
so please understand i am not in any way
criticizing the way the armed forces are
but they named reforms india has one of
the best and most professional armies
and militaries in the world we are proud
of everything they have achieved we are
proud of everything they are still doing
today they are putting their lives on
the line every single day and night
while we are sitting comfortably
wherever we are
so
we are proud of the armed forces but it
does need reforms
the indian army the indian military is
still run the way it was done in the
1960s and 50s 1940s many of these
traditions
and all that the culture it comes back
from the the british raj days that needs
to slowly go we need professionalism we
need what's called lateral intake we
need people who can come and go
for a certain duration and then go back
i mean look at countries where you have
such schemes the uh
the people who have come out of the
armed forces have contributed so much to
society
many u.s presidents where they served in
the marines or the or the air force or
navy or whatever right
john f kennedy is an example
uh george bush's father the the first
bush george bush junior senior he served
in second world war he was shot down by
the japanese
you know
and some people say it's going to lead
to the militarization of society i think
india's society needs a little bit of
militarization and that military
attitude i think that would really help
indian society because right now indian
society you know it's kind of
undisciplined indisciplined
it needs some of that
and
the indian government has said very
clearly that we are not going to take
back the scheme good job don't take it
back and
once this scheme is implemented yes some
things will need to be changed some
tweaks will have to be made that's what
happens with any scheme anywhere in the
world so after one year two years three
years four years five years they're
going to refine the scheme
make some changes and it's going to be
becoming even better and in about a
decades time
what's going to happen is that we will
have more than 1 million trained
reserves who have been released back
into the
civilian population and these trained
reserves are very well they can come in
very handy in times of need
if there is a war
well we you know what kind of
neighborhood we are sitting in in india
we have a bad neighborhood we have very
bad neighbors
in case there is a war and we need to
pull up some reserves you will have a
ready-made
population
of well-trained reserves who can come
back and they know how to handle weapons
they know how the army works they know
how these things work and they'll be
able to fit back
on demand into the armed forces
you know well-trained motivated
patriotic people who have gone through
four years of training and service
i mean it is
an excellent thing now some people will
not agree with it it's fine
today what is the date today
uh today is the 19th of june 2022 take
out your diaries write it down that
abhijit chawla said this on 19th of june
2022 that this is an excellent scheme
then come back in 10 years time open the
diary and then tell then ask yourself
was i right or was i wrong i was right
about the farm laws
the government had to take it back fine
this scheme is even better this is an
excellent scheme for the military for
the nation
people will create the sort of
narrative that it's a bad thing come
back in 10 years time and then see
do a little bit of growing up right now
you may be doubtful because your
favorite influential influencer or
news reader or youtuber or whatever
it has must have told you that this is a
bad scheme come back in 10 years after
you do a bit of growing up and then
and then see
then ask yourself
was this a good skill or a bad scheme
was i right or wrong i'm i guarantee you
like keralo i am right it's an excellent
scheme for india so that is what i have
to say about this and i know lots of
people on both sides these days there
are two wings in india left wing and
right wing and left wing is totally
against the scheme we know that but
plenty of
various influential people on the
so-called right wing are also
disparaging this plan this is the scheme
i'm not naming anybody but we know that
some people are doing that many people
are doing that well they are all wrong
and i wonder why they are doing this
some people are very much anti
anything that this government does and i
find it very strange and perplexing and
i wonder what the motivation is
so i am very clear about this this is an
excellent scheme the agnibat scheme and
we should all support it it's going to
be very beneficial for the country for
the military in the long run the game is
always in the long run not the short
term
all right so i support it one hundred
percent and so should you
purim sudha singh says when did our
millennium of humiliation end and if it
is still continuing when will it end
the millennium of humiliation
has never ended
it is still in force why is it still
enforced because india is still
colonized
all that happened in the last 1000 years
the two waves of colonization the first
was the turkic wave of colonization and
the second was the uh european
wave of colonization
all the effects all the harm they did to
india as a civilization as a culture as
a society and as a modern nation state
that harm still endures
the effects of the colonization are
still visible they are still being lived
by us look at the
language that we are speaking in all
over our media look at what the language
i'm speaking in i am just as mentally
colonized as anybody else
i am more comfortable speaking english
than various other indian languages
yeah unfortunately that's the way we
have been raised brought up and so on we
are still colonized as long as we are
colonized the millennium millennium
affirmation has not ended and the other
thing i would like to say is that uh as
long as india is
there is external interference within
india
as long as india does not have a fully
independent foreign policy and indian
indian in internal policy the the
millennium humiliation has not ended yet
and india right now does not have
it
we have a very good government we have a
very strong government but there are
forces external to india that are still
way too powerful us for us
to resist so they succeed in messing up
our internal affairs and and
pressurizing us on the foreign policy
front we are now pushing back but there
is still a long way to go let me give
you an example we were speaking about
the agni agni path scheme
let me
share something
to give you an example of what i mean by
this
so this is a tweet by
mr vikram sood
the frequency and ease with with which
riots arson and violence for totally
unrelated and trivial issues have been
occurring means that there is a
nationwide well-oiled internal ecosystem
aided by an external facility that
enables this to happen countrywide
furthermore
mr sood says
and let's wait for it to load
hello you gonna load yes so this is a
continuation of the previous tweet this
is not democracy at work but a result of
a sinister campaign designed to create
anarchy and weaken the country
politically economically militarily this
campaign is likely to continue until the
next elections implications not only for
the government but also for the country
mr vikram saw in case you don't know is
the former head
the former head of the research and
intelligence wing raw india's external
intelligence agency mr vikram sood is a
former head
of the iw so he knows what he is saying
he knows what's going on so you when he
when he says this we've got to take it
very seriously what he is implying is
that there is
an internal system
in within india that works against the
indian national interest and this is all
supported by an external
external forces and external powers
that's what he is saying that's
precisely what i mean so we are still
or if we are still being coerced and
bullied and pushed around and our
internal affairs are being
well there is interference internally by
foreign powers and there is pressure
on us visa with the foreign policy also
by certain foreign powers we know who
they are so it's still going on
so the humiliation of the millennium of
human humiliation has not ended we are
still living through it
it will end when india regains its
historical position
economically military and
civilizationally that's when the
millennium affirmation will officially
end we are far from that yet it may
still be another 50 or 100 years
depending on what we do today as a
people as a country as a civilization
and each what each of us individually
does for the country so it all
rests in the hands of individuals and
the government
so it's not ended yet
okay domur akil says i am from mauritius
last year the international court of
justice gave mauritius the sovereignty
over the chago archipelago
but the american army is not leaving
diego garcia and recently the mauritian
flag was taken down on the island of
perez-banos
could you give an explanation of what's
happening there what is the geographical
importance
why are no countries debating this good
question
whenever we talk about these issues we
you know what i'm going to do
i'm going to pull up the map where's the
map where's the map
let me find the map
where is the map
um the map here's the map come on map
here we are all right
so akil is talking about the chago
archipelago vis-a-vis mauritius so what
is where is mauritius once again
so we know where india is this here is
india the indian subcontinent this is
the indonesian region which
well
essentially should be our backyard
and if you go south we have the two
islands of mauritius in the reunion
and if we go further north towards the
seychelles you will find
uh further north from seychelles
south of the maldives
okay here not north from the seychelles
eastern station okay here we are
this is the chago archipelago this
entire thing it's it's a bunch of
islands it's an archipelago
and the largest
uh
island is this one here
diego garcia
it's called the british indian ocean
territory so what is the story here
right
so mauritius claims that this belongs to
them that the
this region the chago archipelago is
under mauritian sovereignty mauritius
should have the sovereignty over this
region so what is the dispute what is
the history right
uh let me close this for a while uh so
that you understand what's happening
okay
so that's the question once again so
what what what is the dispute all about
let's look back at the history of the
place right so it all begins in the 19th
century i think in the early 19th
century around 1815
1814 uh the british
acquired took over possession of the
chago archipelago this bunch of islands
now the this was not some uninhabited
bunch of islands there were people
living there the shagosyan people so
these people their ancestry is mostly
african madagascar mozambique other
eastern african nations
and there is eventually later on there
there came to be a significant amount of
indian and malay malaysian malay
ancestry
including many people from mauritius who
were were brought there and made to
settle down there
so the british in the 19th century took
over seychelles and the mauritius as
well and mauritius as well which i just
showed you on the map right
uh so
how did indians end up there so that is
something i need to explain to you as
well
so let me
share
my screen once again
so in the 19th century the british
they sent a bunch of indian indentured
workers
uh into the two various places in
various parts of the world
half a million were transported to
mauritius when you say indentured
workers it's a nice word for slaves the
british took indians as essentially as
slaves they would pay them a little
amount of money so technically it's not
slavery but it's nothing but slavery so
these people were taken against their
wishes and they were transported to this
far-off places in the world and they
were moved there forever they had no way
of coming back to india ever and their
descendants still live there so half a
million almost two mauritius another 150
000 1.5 lakhs to eastern africa uh
southern africa south africa and uh
tanzania et cetera kenya that region
east africa and another half a million
to uh the west indies
to places like uh
guyana
trinidad
and so on right so the west indies east
africa and mauritius ill maurice
so that's where indians were transported
from mauritius some of them were
transported to chago
so the chagosian people
their ancestry is african and some
indian and some malay malay ancestry so
that is what this ethnic group is like
now so this was the 19th century that's
what happened in the early 20th century
around 1903 or so seychelles
was separated from this uh
from the british possessions it became a
separate it was administered separately
right now the reason why the british
took over all these all these islands
in the indian ocean region was to
consolidate their
hold over this vital
piece of maritime real estate they they
wanted to control all the input
the exit points all the sea routes and
all that and what better way to do it
than to control various territories in
various islands and various archipelagos
in this region strategic locations from
which you can in which you can place
your navy and control the entire region
right so that's why they did that and of
course you the more territory you
acquire and administer the more power
you have over the whole world
so uh in 1902 1903 seychelles was
separated
and they kept on administering uh
mauritius and shago
now now in 1956 the british were already
weakened by the disaster in the second
world war uh the us was the dominant
power then there was this swiss crisis
in 1956 that's a whole different story
very interesting and very uh it's kind
of forgotten today what happened in
swaze but it kind of changed world
history so 1956 was the suez
crisis it was all about control of the
suez canal
port saeed
and the that region
uh
and the british wanted to control it the
egyptians tried wanted to nationalize it
there was a war there and the americans
eventually armed twisted the british and
the french into getting out of there and
from that day onwards the british were
essentially
of the americans
so after 1956 after the disaster in the
sales crisis the british
decided to withdraw east of suez
yeah
so they decided to withdraw from their
territorial positions east of suez
in 1965 the british what they did was
they separated the sago archipelago from
mauritius yeah separate administrative
division in 1965 itself there was a u.s
uk agreement
which gave the
americans kind of possession of the
chago archipelago especially the diego
garcia
island right and they would use it for
military purposes
in 1968 mauritius was given independence
but chago archipelago was not made part
of that
right and the mauritius government has
always claimed that as part of their
territory because it was i mean
technically for the longest time it was
part it was administered from mauritius
and the people also have links to
mauritius but the british said
refused to do that and they gave it to
the us
in 2016 the lease of the us was extended
by another 20 years
so let's take a look at diego garcia
what does this place look like
diego garcia so the chago archipelago
actually is
an extension
of the lakshadweep and maldives system
okay maldives
uh historically culturally is part of
the indian uh civilization indian
subcontinent the people of maldives are
of indian origin they're the same
ethnicity as people in southern india
and they all they have in maldivian
history they have always known about the
archipelago
it was quite a way south from the
maldives but maldivians would go there
from time to time sometimes in during
storms they would get shipwrecked there
and they would have to be rescued and so
on so historically before the european
intrusion into this region it was you
could say part of the greater indian
territory
chago archipelago
now the british indian territory diego
garcia this is what it looks like okay
it's it's a wonderfully
constructed
uh island
there is this is entirely more or less
run by the us
this is the diego garcia airport a very
important strategic location for the us
from which they can essentially watch
over everything that's happening in the
in indonesian region they can keep an
eye on what india is doing
they can keep an eye on india's
activities naval activities military
activities other activities they can
keep an eye on the chinese what the
chinese are doing and what's happening
in sri lanka it's it's a prime
centrally located
location
so that's why the u.s
wants this and they they want to hang on
to it right
so
and in 2016 they got another extension
of 20 years about 30 about three to five
thousand american
military personnel are typically
stationed at diego garcia at any given
point of time
in 2017
the international court of justice said
that they should go back to mauritius it
should be it belongs to mauritius and
then later on the international tribune
tribunal for the law of the sea also
said that this should go to mauritius it
belongs to mauritius and it is
administered illegally
by the uk and by extension by the u.s so
so the uh
so it's very clear what the u.n what the
international court of justice was what
the international tribune for tribunal
for the law of the sea they are all in
agreement that this should belong to
mauritius and they have ordered the uk
to give it back to mauritius it's not
happened they have taken no action about
this the americans are also supporting
the uk which is very strange because
they talk about a rules-based
international order
what happened to their precious
rules-based international order
when it came to a dispute between the
philippines and the chinese when the
international tribunal for the law of
the sea ruled in favor of the
philippines the americans supported that
yeah
the americans supported the ruling when
it was in favor of the philippines but
now when it's in favor of the of the
mauritians and the tragosians the
americans don't want are
refusing to agree to it
so what happened to the rules based in
international order it it they will
support it when it is in favor of
when it's in their favor
and they will refuse to to agree to it
when it's not in their favor
this
makes the u.s look very bad and they're
not going to give it up they want to
hang on to diego garcia it's very
important for them
but what then they should stop the
hypocrisy about this rules-based
international order and all that
so that is what's happening that's why
it's geographically important that's why
it's geopolitically important and why is
nobody debating about this because the
americans are all powerful you don't
want to offend them
that's what it is the the uk doesn't
matter the uk is a pushover the uk
is well
a vasal state of the us
the chinese uh would say on on their
global times twitter account that the uk
are lapdogs of the us i don't say that
the chinese say that okay so that's how
it is so the uk doesn't matter it's the
u.s that's holding on to this territory
and that it's it's important because
it's a it's a very
well geographically located place
centrally located and it's a very
good uh
the island its geography is very good
for having a large
naval and air force base there and
that's why they want to hold on to it
and they don't really care about rules
and laws or anything it's all about
holding on to everything they have so
that's what it is so that's what's
happening i don't see anything going
in favor of the people of chago uh the
mauritians recently uh
landed there and did something but
obviously not a diego garcia i'm sure
somewhere else like you said uh
on the island of peros banos and so on
so the americans will
i mean the mauritius the mauritians are
just a small little country com they are
well
just an island nation right
and in geopolitics might is right it's
the law of the jungle
and that's just how it works so that's
what's happening and nobody wants to
offend the americans so no one's talking
about it
human rights and justice and fairness
and equality and rules rules based order
these are nice words to use when it's
when it suits you but it actually has no
real meaning so unfortunately that's
where we are
okay this is by darshan asking for this
asking this for the 480 second time why
do some castes like brahmins and juts
have more step in eastern european
ancestry than the other castes in the
indian subcontinent is it due to the
aryan imagination theory or something
else reply please and so on yeah okay
darshan
so there is no such thing as a caste
all right there is there are japanese
and varnas and all that the cast term is
a
is a colonial imposition upon us and so
on but let's not go there let's talk
about the so-called step ancestry and
all that so what is this
wonderful step ancestry let's go back to
the map where's the map here's the map
so what is the step the step is the the
the
certain
region
across eurasia all the way from
manchuria in the east you know this here
here if you can see my mouse pointer
this this region is manchuria
all the way from here across mongolia if
you can see where mongolia is yeah this
is mongolia
from kazakhstan
all the way to ukraine belarus eastern
asia eastern europe
and southern parts of russia
continental eurasia and russia all of
that is the eurasian step or stippy or
whatever you want to call it that is the
step
now in the aryan invasion migration
tourism picnic etc theory
apparently for the longest time the
researchers
used to say
that
there was an iron invasion then it was a
migration and so on and it came from the
step from the eurasian step that's what
they claimed
and
there is clear affinity between indian
populations and populations of
europe
we know that
we all know that
and some components some genetic
components are higher in some
some parts of india and
there is more similarity between some
parts of india and some parts of europe
and so on and so forth which is
obviously bound to happen because there
is common genetic origin we all know
that the only question is where does it
where did it originate
we all know that uh 70 80 000 years ago
we were our ancestors were in africa so
from from africa they moved into eurasia
they wandered around eventually they
settled down in india india was the
original founders zone of the out of
africa migration from india there were
migrations to all parts of eurasia
we met the neanderthals we interbred
with them
most non-african humans have some
neanderthal ancestry indians
mostly don't have it for some reason and
so on long story
now the story the real question is the
aryan invasion thing migration thing the
real question central question is what
is the origin of sanskrit and hinduism
it's not a genetic question at all it's
all about the what is the origin of
sanskrit the indo-european languages and
the
ancient
indo-european culture which is hinduism
that is the real question and everyone
that is the the question they are trying
to
they're trying to say it came from out
of india so they want to portray
indian culture as being in a predatory
invasive culture and sanskrit as well
that is the whole crux of the story and
they wrap it inside these genetic
stories and all that there is no link
actual link between genetics and
languages genetics and culture but
that's a different story the question is
about the brahmins and so on why do they
have more
step ancestry
so this term step ancestry it's a nice
tag that they have constructed and when
you use this tag yesterday there was a
question that i got that can a person
with no scientific training
tell whether a certain piece of research
is authentic or not and there is no way
a person without scientific training can
tell whether research is authentic or
not so it's very easy to mislead people
by somebody pausing and posing as an
expert and saying hey this is what has
happened
there are certain
business journalists who have written
books nowadays tony joseph who's written
written a book about the uh the what
early indians or some sort thing
terrible book i have reviewed it
terrible book
all lies
all distortions and
all that so
what is this step ancestry it is a term
it is a term uh uh they have created it
is a tag they have attached attached to
a certain group of genes step ancestry
and it's supposed to be the overall
um
source of the indo-european arya
so-called aryan ethnicity and languages
and culture
so they say that this so-called step
ancestry this this certain genetic
component is the entire origin
of all indo-european languages and
culture
and they have given it the title of step
ancestry they could have given it a
different title martian ancestry then we
would all imagine that our people came
from mars
right
now the question is
what is the origin of the so-called step
in history
they say that there was a group of
people in the eurasian step
who then came to india to iran and they
went westwards and they are the origin
originators the pre-pregenators of the
indo-european peoples and languages and
culture
this they say happened about five or six
thousand years before today
my question is very simple where did
those people come from
the people who gave rise to the safe
step so-called step ancestry where did
their ancestors come from answer that
question can they answer it apparently
nowadays we can
so let's find out what that is one
second
so
there are a number of famous geneticists
in the world
we have our own
geneticist
famous geneticist his name is dr niraj
rai but when i talk about dr niraja
people say oh he's indian indians don't
know anything give us a different source
a western source
you know gurkhi murgi dal barabar dr
nirajira is one of the best geneticists
in the world but people don't want to
talk about him so okay let's talk about
somebody else i have a whole
conversation with dr nirajara about this
various about the same topic but let me
talk about somebody else
so
let us talk about the great
renowned dr david reich
reich
so this is
a lecture that dr wright reich
gave on the 12th
of july 2022
a week before today
last sunday he gave this lecture okay
the title of the lecture is the genetic
history of the southern ark a bridge
between west asia and europe
okay
so what is this southern ark
the southern ark is an area divided
geographically between west asia and
europe
which we define as spanning the
culturally entangled regions of anatolia
and its neighbors
in both europe asia and the balkans and
in west asia cyprus armenia the levant
iraq and iran
so that is
what he defines as the southern ark
the eastern region of the southern ark
is iraq and iran
now what does this lecture all about and
what does it say let's look at the
the last
paragraph a striking signal of step
migration into the southern arc is
evident in armenia in northwest iran
where admixture with the yamnaya
patrilineal descendants occurred
coinciding with the third millennium bce
displacement from the step itself this
ancestry pervasive across numerous sites
of armenia from 2000 to 600 bc was
diluted blah blah blah blah blah
the impermeability of anatolia to
exogenous migration contrasts with our
finding that the yamnia had two distinct
gene flows both from west asia
suggesting that the indo-anatolian
language family
originated in the eastern wing of the
southern ark and that the steppe served
only as a secondary staging area
of the indo-european language dispersal
can you see what this great famous
gentleman is saying here
the step served as a secondary staging
area of indo-european language dispersal
yeah
and the
so the yamnia had two distinct gene
flows both from west asia
right and what was the thing about
eastern uh where is it eastern um one
second let me search for it
yeah the indo-anatolian language family
originated in the eastern wing of the
southern ark what is the eastern wing of
the southern ark that he spoke about let
me just quickly show you on the map what
this eastern wing is talking about
one second let me go on the map and show
you the eastern wing
where is the map here's the map
where's the map come on map
the eastern wing that he speaks about
is iran
all right
so now so until now they were saying
that the so-called step ancestry
originated in in central asia in the
central asian step eurasian step
now in a round about complicated way dr
reich is saying
that the step itself was a secondary
point of dispersal
what was it saying
uh
the step served as a secondary staging
area of the indo-european dispersal
language dispersal and genetic dispersal
and the actual staging the actual origin
seems to be in the eastern
ah what eastern eastern wing of the
southern
ark which is now iran
so slowly
10 years ago they were saying it is the
central asian step now they are saying
it is the eastern wing of the southern
ark which is iran
and if you
watch my conversation with doctor nilla
he is very clear that geographically
iran is part of the indian subcontinent
because why do i say this why does it
say this because if you want to go from
from central asia into india it is
extraordinarily difficult there are so
many mountain ranges to cause cross it's
very cold you will die you will most
likely die but if you want to cross from
india into iran you just have to carry
some water and maybe a donkey or a camel
and some food and you just have to walk
walk west and you will easily reach
around there's nothing in the way
so india and iran it is part of this
extended geographical region of the
indian subcontinent
so what dr reich is saying
that the so-called step ancestry
actually originates in the southern wing
of the
in the eastern wing of the southern ark
it originates in iraq two three years
down the line he will quietly make a
more complicated statement saying it
originates for the east in
italy he will now see pakistan in
afghanistan and in 10 years time they
will say india
let us be very clear about this
let us be very clear about this when
they say step ancestor we have to ask
them where is the origin of the step
answers to itself
and this
link that i just showed you this lecture
that dr reich gave last week
in that he is saying that this step
ancestry doesn't originate in the step
it originates in iran he's saying now
after some more genetic data is going to
come up this year there's going to be an
r1a paper that will be published from
india
once that paper is probably dr reich
will say that the
the step ancestry originates essentially
from the indus valley region
it's going to happen
so all of this complicated
discussion all of these these
complicated topics actually
you have to ask a very simple question
what is the origin of it all
the so-called step ancestry where did
that come from
were they born in the step with those
human beings that they originated from
the ground or did they migrate from
somewhere else of course they migrated
from somewhere else
that is the question and at the end of
the day when all the data is out
when sufficient data is revealed it's
going to be very clear it all came from
the indian subcontinent whether it is
iran or further east from iran most
likely it's further east from iran
because we know very well the iranians
are descendants of ancient indians it's
very clear
so that is the crux of the matter wait
for some time patience
patience i advocate patience
in the next five years all of all of
these people they're gonna sing the same
story
and the step ancestry will say will
originate from india it's going to
happen
right gagan chengapa says as but as per
tv serials
the great man ashok got betrayals
one of that was that his mother was
killed from the childhood itself so he
took revenge by killing his brothers
okay
tell me something let's say i am a kid
let's say i'm 15 years old i want to be
a great scientist i want to be a
scientist
how should i study science should i
watch science fiction movies and serials
to learn science
or should i spend hundreds of hours
studying science from actual proper
textbooks and solving thousands of
problems and investing the time and the
effort and the hard work into actually
reading
and studying
can you
become a great scientist
very proficient in science quantum
mechanics relativity whatever by
watching tv serials about science
no you can't similarly if you want to
understand history please stop watching
tv series it's entertainment it's
fiction
if you want to learn actual history
please stop relying on tv serials read
there is no substitute for reading there
is no substitute for hard work i
understand that this is the maybe you
don't have access to books so please
dear friend
please if you are really interested in
history
invest in at least one or two good
history books
from about let's say the mauryan era or
whatever whichever
phase of indian history you're
interested in
invest in a couple of books read those
books
and that will give you a better
perspective than tv serials tv series is
all about viewership it's all about
creating interest and the best way to
create interest is by distorting history
and saying oh my god everything you've
been taught is wrong
right so please that's not the way to
study history okay thank you
baka nani says if you compare the
achievements and personality of
chandragupta maurya and his grandson
ashok
who comes out as more successful who is
truly worthy of the title the great
so chandragupta maurya and his
descendant ashok grandson ashok who was
greater who was
who is more successful so let's see
where the two came from let's begin with
ashok ashok was the son of a great
mauryan emperor
right
so his father was already the emperor of
all of india
and all he did was he
he took over
the reigns of the kingdom the crown from
his father in whatever way was best he
killed off his siblings his half
siblings and he put down various
rebellions and so on because he was
killing people and so on and he waged a
few wars he
committed committed this atrocity in
kalinga
and then he said okay now i'm done i'm
now peace
and then he uplifted this obscure
sect philosophical sect called the
called the
both the sect and he turned it into a
global force
that's what ashok did
so what great struggle did he undergo he
killed off all his siblings and step
siblings and he waged a few wars and he
crushed a few rebellions that's what he
did what did chandragupta did
do what did chandragupta maurya do
he was born
in obscurity
he was not royalty
he had no royal lineage he was most
likely an orphan
we don't even know who his parents were
right so he had
he was not born with a silver spoon in
his mouth like ashok
he was not born
as a prince he was born
in obscurity baby in poverty we don't
know what he was born as we don't know
who his parents were he was an orphan
and he obviously exhibited certain
traits
that the great vishnu of the chanakya
noticed and he recognized that that
there is some potential in this boy
and what vaishnavaki did was he trained
this boy in straight statecraft and
various other matters like maybe
military arts and strategy and tactics
and all that
and with the help of the great vishnu
gupta chanakya under his mentorship
this unknown boy of obscure origins
went on
to become
in a span of about 20 years the emperor
of all of india he conquered the whole
of india the story of how he did that is
not even well known
so if you compare chandragupta maurya
with ashok there is no question about
who was greater who was more successful
chandragupta maurya was the most
successful of all of the mauryan
emperors the greatest of them all
he created an empire from nowhere i
speak about napoleon i have a video on
this channel about napoleon which i
speak about in brief about his history
that he went from obscurity to emperor
in about 19 years
chandragupta did something way greater
than that
way greater than what napoleon achieved
there was an existing empire the nanda
empire which was most likely in power
when the alleged invasion by elegantly
happened most likely it was the
nandazura in power
and within 20 years the entirety of the
indian subcontinent was ruled by
chandragupta
so that is an incredible spectacular
achievement there is no question about
who is greater it was chandragupta
maurya who is greater
samhita says why does the english
language have so many different accents
all over the world what is the main
history behind these actions which one
is the oldest you know it's very funny
but it randomly strikes my mind okay
see in every part of the world there are
different languages
within india which is a vast
subcontinent we have different languages
some languages sound very different
so people who grow up in this region
speaking a certain mother tongue they
will acquire certain phonetic traits
certain ways of pronouncing pronouncing
certain sounds
right
so
when you speak a foreign language some
of your native uh
accents and pronunciations will come
into it
so that's why when indians speak english
they speak it in a certain way the
certain actions when the japanese speak
english they speak it in a different way
they don't say sorry this is solly
they don't say english they say english
and so on the chinese speak english in a
different way
the africans do and so on and similarly
if you were asked if you were to ask
somebody from france to speak hindi they
would speak in with hindi with the for
with a french accent
if somebody from china speaks hindi they
would speak it with a chinese accent
imagine hypothetically imagine some
italian person speaking hindi how will
that sound
just imagine it's never happened but
maybe you you could think of something
so that's how it is everybody has a
certain native accent and any language
they speak will be infused with their
native accent and that's why whether
it's english whether it's hindi whether
it is swahili
when somebody who is non-native speaks
that language they will
add their own native accent and
pronunciation to it so that's why it
happens
okay hedgehog's dilemma says if pakistan
fragments what path will go to india
it's very clear if if not if when
pakistan fragments
kashmir
the entirety of kashmir will come back
to india
the paths that are under illegal
pakistani occupation uh gilgit baldistan
and the pakistan occupied kashmir that
will immediately come back to india we
will deal with the chinese occupied
trucks gun valley in due course that
also will return to india in due course
no doubt about it
so when pakistan fragments that's what's
going to happen immediately
p okay
we'll come back to india immediately
what else will happen the other parts of
pakistan punjab pakistani punjab western
punjab
sindh
balochistan
northwest frontier province or
pashtunistan all these will not come to
we don't want them to come to india
are we really prepared to absorb to
reabsorb
a radicalized terrorist population into
india i'm not saying all pakistanis are
terrorists
i have nothing against the pakistani
people i have said this on various
channels yeah nothing personal against
them they are our people the same blood
same dna same ancestry nothing against
them
right but
this is a highly radicalized population
see what they are taught see last week
what one of the pakistani teachers
professor college or professor the
college professor
wrote what they are teaching what the
students are taught they are taught
poison against india
so this is a highly radicalized
population there is a significant
percentage of the population
non-trivial percentage of the population
that supports terrorism
and the significant
percentage of them want india destroyed
do we want to re-observe those people
right now no we don't
let sin become sindhudesh independent
let balochistan become independent
balochistan
let pastor nistan return to afghanistan
let the pashtuns finally have their
unified homeland i'll be very happy to
see that
let uh
pakistani punjab become its own country
good for them
yeah
and kashmir obviously will return to
india so that's what will happen and
maybe in 50 years hundred years we will
de-radicalize them slowly
there are certain d whatever programs
happening right now ukraine has been
denatified
and so on so we will eventually slowly
over time deradicalize them and when the
time is right we will reabsorb them into
the motherland of india
that's a long term project 50 years
hundred years but immediately when the
country is fragmented those nations
should be those territories should be
given independence kashmir should be
reabsorbed into india but the islam goes
back to afghanistan and the other
territories become independent countries
that's what should happen immediately
devastating says may the force be with
you yes thank you what should be our
strategy in the indian ocean region to
create dominance and how
far in the ocean should we aim for
dominance okay good question let's go to
the map here's the map
here's our app
the indian ocean region is the entire
region south of the indian subcontinent
so this is the indian subcontinent as
you know and the entire region south of
it
is the indian ocean region which goes
which
extends from the
coastline of indonesia
burma the andaman sea all the way to
western australia
down to antarctica and we also also
talking about east the eastern coast of
africa madagascar
somalia kenya tanzania mozambique south
africa and of course the
eastern parts the eastern coast of the
arabian peninsula all of this is the
indian ocean region and india occupies a
god-gifted dominant geographical
position in this region if india wants
in 10 years it can dominate the entire
region if it builds a strong enough navy
so the answer is very simple in order to
dominate this region india needs to have
a powerful navy and is
and
what goes along with that is a powerful
air force
so what do we do
so what we need to immediately aim for
is we need to in the next five to ten
years be able to on demand choke off
access to the various strategic choke
points in the region one is the strait
of bab al-mandeb here between the red
sea and the gulf of aden
it's a very narrow region if you if you
dominate this region with your navy you
can choke it off
same for goes for the strait of hormuz
over here
between
the portion gulf and the gulf of oman
that's a very important strategic choke
point
then there are two other choke points
the gulf the strait of malacca and the
sunda straight over here
so that's where all the chinese shipping
goes through and of course we have the
andaman sea there are the very strategic
this is a very strategic region or much
of the shooting goes through the andaman
sea to the andaman decor islands and the
luxury violence
so what india needs to do to dominate
this region is first of all build a
strong enough navy to dominate these
choke points
and we don't want more aircraft carriers
people keep on saying that object is
stupid he says aircraft carriers are not
important they are not important we have
unsinkable aircraft carriers already all
these islands in the andaman region the
nikova region are unsinkable aircraft
carriers the lakshadweep islands are
unsinkable aircraft carriers we don't
need to to invest tens of billions of
dollars into building this slow moving
ships that are massive targets
we can leverage the geographical
advantage we already have that same
money can be invested in building
invisible deadly submarines the
submarines are the most dangerous ship
in the navy naval world today in the
21st century in the 20th century the
capital ship of every navy was the
aircraft carrier in the 21st century the
capital ship of any navy is the
submarine we need to invest in submarine
submarines nuclear submarines
conventional submarines lots of
submarines that's what we need
and of course we should have a visible
presence in the indian ocean so we can
build uh
lots of cheap
uh
what do you call them uh coast guard
ships vessels
each vessel should not cost more than 10
15 20 million dollars and you could even
put brahmos missiles on them you know
you can
engineer it properly so you could have
hundreds of brahmos missiles in the
indonesian at our back and they can call
at our disposal
all these steps we should minimize the
expenses and maximize the numbers
because quantity has a quality of its
own we don't have a huge amount of money
to throw into this so we need to be
smart smart just like isro
achieves so much on such a tight budget
similarly we can do a similar thing in
the naval domain as well and maximize
our assets with the least amount of
money so build lots of cheap submarines
build a few very expensive nuclear
submarines for sure
and build lots of surface vessels which
are cheap and disposable like uh
like coast guard vessels equipped with
missiles missile boats missile boats are
an underrated and very potent naval
asset
we destroyed karachi in 71 with missile
boats not with big warships so these are
the things that we should do and if we
do that we'll be able to dominate the
indonesian region we can achieve that in
the next 10 years if we get our things
together the problem is that the
military has a certain way of thinking
which goes back to the 20th century
unfortunately that's why we need fresh
blood in the military fresh ideas
i know i sound like a armchair general
sitting in an air conditioned office and
talking all kinds of things but hey i i
know what i'm talking about i've been
studying this all my life and if you
don't believe me you can
watch my interview with my conversation
with dr edward luther one of the
greatest jio strategists who is still
alive today and he echoes what i'm
saying
he says that aircraft carriers are not
needed they are obsolete
submarines are what any
forward-looking navy with big ambitions
would invest in
watch my conversation with dr edward
luther one of the best one of the most
interesting conversations i've had in my
whole life watch that
all right next question
niccolo says the video is interesting if
the yamnya were from the indian
subcontinent i think dr reich also
conquers nowadays so if the yamnaya
where from the indian subcontinent why
didn't the vedic dharma
restrain their savagely violent impulses
if your theory is true it undermines the
narrative of a peaceful bharat that
doesn't invade other nations
this narrative is false
that bharata is a peaceful nation that
doesn't invade other nations
no
we are not a peaceful nation that
doesn't invade other nations
have you heard of the cholas
the cholas were bharatiyas right great
emperors rajaraj and rajendra chola what
did they do did they not invade and
conquer the whole of southeast asia
the cholas did that
what did the guptas do
whether it is
that is kumar gupta or
gupta embers emperors they invaded all
the way up central asia
bahalik bulk and so on conquered that
region
what did the kushans do what did lalith
he conquered much of central asia
kanishka the great
a great the one of the greatest indian
emperors
what did he do his empire
stretched from the caspian sea to the
rlc to the entirety of xinjiang
chinese occupied xinjiang and so on and
so forth we have always been
a militaristically expansive power
we've always been that whenever india
has been unified under a single emperor
it has been this way it's never been a
peaceful
non-violent country that doesn't invade
no no no that is not true absolutely not
true
if you study history you will know that
this is you will know that this is a lie
so indians have always
been
vigorous
in military in the military sphere we
have been a maritime civilization always
we've always expanded in various
directions troubled whether it's for
trade whether it's for peaceful purposes
whether it's for spreading culture and
civilization or whether it's for
military conquest we have done that in
the past we will do that again in the
future we will conquer again
we are still
we're still waking up okay in the coming
decades india is going to go back to its
roots and india will conquer again no
apologies
so the question about the yamnaya yes
they were from the indian subcontinent
they they have the haplogroup r1b which
is a descendant of r1 which is a
descendant of r which is eventually
descendant of f which are all indian
origin haplogroups
and this year the indian team is going
to
led by dr nirajai and co-worker
collaborators is going to finally
release the paper publish the paper
about the origins of r1 r1a i believe
and
so it's going to throw some clarity on
this matter further clarity
so the amnio
where from the indian subcontinent the
step ancestry so called right we just
saw that the step ancestor nowadays
originates from iran eventually it will
originate from the ganga region ganga
valley so
the yamnia were from the indian
subcontinent so why did the vedic dharma
not restrain their savagely violent
impulses because we know it is known
that the armonia decimated the whole of
europe they rampaged through the
entirety of eurasia they wiped out
native populations of europe the
original native populations of europe
only the males not the females and then
they intermingled with the females
and produced descendants who are the
europeans of today so today's europeans
their ancestry is
patronelia
is paternally from the amnio and
maternally from the original european
peoples that's what it is so why did
these people
who were indians of indian origin why
did they behave in such a savage
violent and brutal and barbaric manner
when their ancestral culture was the
vedic culture which is a very peaceful
culture why is that so
well
there are a number of
things that one can speak about when it
comes to this firstly
we kind of see tend to believe that our
vedic ancestors
were very philosophical
peaceful people who believed in
meditation
and non-violence 24 by 7 that's not the
case
they were just as
vigorous
and ambitious
as we are today
our vedic ancestors were also warriors
we had a number of vedic clans who were
always
vying for territory and advantage of
advantages of various kinds we have the
very famous famous event the
the battle or war of ten kings which
actually involved more than ten kings
and it is the bharata clan that came out
on top under the great king sudas
right who was the son of the great
devotee son of grandson of devadas so
sudhas who was the king of the bharata
clan prevailed and all the losers were
booted out of india and they went
westward and northwards
right so
and one of the the
clans that was defeated was the parshwa
clan the persua people who went westward
and populated persia persia takes its
name from the pursuit of the vedic
indians
now it is possible that one of the
offshoots of the the the people who lost
the clans who lost may have been the
ancestors of the um yamnia possibly
it's a possibility i'm not saying we
know we have proof but it's a
possibility so what happened to those
people who went westward northwards
they left the indian subcontinent
and they settled they went and settled
down
and migrated westwards and settled in
various parts of of eurasia central asia
and eventually they went all the way
west into europe we know that we know
that
after they left the indian subcontinent
they were their umbilical cord their
umbilical ties to the motherland was cut
off
were cut off
and over time they
they shed
the vedic rituals in rights and culture
and customs
so
if you look at the various ancient
indian texts they are referred to the
people of central asia uttarakhand
not ethnically but culturally
because they
have abandoned the vedic dharma they
don't practice it fully
they don't honor the vedic rituals fully
they practice some of them but not all
of them they are lacks
and there is some laxity in their
behavior and they have acquired some
barbaric traits and so on so that's why
they are called lectures the yavanas the
ionians were all some lectures they also
would have eventually originally had
some
uh some
vedic
culture but eventually they gave it up
so over time as the distance as the time
increase in the distance from the
homeland increased the culture changed
their pantheon of gods remained the same
all across eurasia until the advent of
christianity you had the same culture in
various local manifestations whether it
was the celtic culture or the nordic
culture or the teutonic culture or the
germanic culture or the italic culture
or the ionian culture the greek culture
carthagini not the carthaginian culture
but whatever whatever
santorini and so on they all had various
local manifestations of the same ancient
indo-european culture which originates
from india the vedic culture the vedic
pantheon of gods
is the same
is the is the template for the greek
pantheon the roman pantheon and the
viking pantheon of gods same gods with
different names same stories
so
they retained the core elements of the
culture but they
they started exhibiting
laxity in the in the way they lived
their lives
so slowly they lost
the ethics and morality that are the
bedrock of dharma
if you see europe the celtic people etc
they had all these blood letting in
human sacrifice and animal sacrifice and
all that which you never find in vedic
dharma
right in in vedic dharma the most you
have is ashwamedhi yagna sometimes you
have
certain other medas also but it's it's a
it's a very rare ritual
so things changed culture changed and
eventually these people who went and
lived in central asia they felt they
were free from the motherland there was
no no need to carry on the same culture
the same ethics same morality
they started living on horseback started
the entire land was empty of people so
just go wherever you can
and whatever else whatever belongs to
other people if you can do if you can
take it you take it and slowly they
became more and more barberized
so ethnically they were still of indian
origin but they had given up their
indian culture in indian morality and
ethics and dharma
and they became barbarians and you see
the result
we see what they did in europe they
conquered the whole of europe and their
descendants are today's europeans
so that's what happened
right that's what happened things change
aman prasad says why does the national
media ignore northeast of india
eastern india northeast especially
southern india also is it done by the
political class to keep india divided
country or is it a problem of media only
it's a political thing it's a media
thing it's a lot the entire
establishment after 1947 was daily
centric
it was all delhi centric everything was
delhi delhi
right
and there was a time
when the central government would have
incredible amounts of power they could
dismiss any state government any time
they wanted for whatever flimsy reason
or pretext and
and entire regions of india were totally
marginalized if you see the amount of
development you have if you take the map
of india where's the map of india here's
the map
here's the map if you see the map of
india
yeah
from top to bottom
including the andaman nicobar and luxury
and all that and if you divide if you if
you draw an imaginary dividing line
between
ladakh
and the kanyakumari
if you take the western half of that of
of the
country
starting from that imaginary dividing
line you will see a certain amount of
development in the west half of western
half of the country and if you see the
eastern half of the country you will see
much less development there
so most of the development in india
happened in the western part of india
since 1947 the eastern part of india was
totally ignored and the further east you
went the more marginalization you had so
the north east of india was totally
completely marginalized until the 2010s
until the 2015s it's only now that we
are seeing progress
in
the so-called northeast of india which
is actually the far east of india
states like nagaland manipur meghalaya
assam etc were totally marginalized
there was no development no job
prospects nothing there separatism was
rife for decades insurgencies were going
on
and the state the central government
simply didn't care and many state
governments maybe not all many of them
were deeply deeply corrupt
and and they were hand in glove with all
kinds of various elements
all aided and abetted and encouraged
from the center
for the longest time
so this is very much a political thing
and of course the indian media
was all patronized by the politicians
especially the central government so
they also totally ignored what was
happening in the northeast there would
be all kinds of things happening which
would never find any coverage in the
media
the so the problem is the most acute in
the northeast even today people don't
know what is the capital of let's say uh
mizoram or what's the capital of of uh
let's say meghalaya
yeah what's the capital of arunachal
doesn't even know that most people don't
know anything about these places people
have never been there and is in the past
when somebody from the northeast of
india would come to a large city they
would people would think they are from
china or something that's the kind of
and it's not the common person's fault
that they had these sort of notions it's
because the education system did not
teach anyone that this region is an
integral integral
and essential part of india and these
people are as indian as everybody else
we were never taught this
so it's
the cause of all of this is first of all
the government and political political
apathy secondly the education system
completely ignored the northeast thirdly
the media didn't care the media was did
whatever the political masters told it
uh told it and so on
so and and the same goes for many parts
of southern india
and that is why there is a sense of
marginalization among certain certain
populations of south india southern
southern india that the entire indian
political landscape is north dominated
the media is not dominated and so on and
there is an element of truth to this
and this causes
divisions in society
and people from various parts of india
start resenting people from other parts
of india when those people have done
nothing it is the politicians the
education system and the media that have
caused these problems but the anti-pathy
goes towards the population towards the
residents of various other parts of
india
so that is
how great a way is that of creating
divisions in indian society
instead of integrating indian society
together you are dividing it further and
of course you have various religious
and political agendas that go hand in
hand
and so on
so that's why
there are all these problems
the southern part of india is ignored
uh
in kashmir the whole of ladakh was
ignored for the longest time people not
people thought everything is kashmir the
kashmir
whatever the problem is is is relegated
and confined to a small valley
but that dominates the entire region
as if all of that is also part of the
problem so that's how that's the kind of
narrative the media constructs that's
why people don't trust the media anymore
the media cannot be trusted
no
in in the media also today you have two
different
groups
left wing and right wing nationalistic
and international whatever i don't trust
any of them
there may be some good people in there
and some channels may be really good but
overall
they are all
well it's a business
and they will do whatever it takes to
to create controversies
you know that's what they do some some
small protest is happening 20 people are
protesting and you will have 50 cameras
around them 20 people are protesting in
some part of a city no one cares but
there are 50
cameras video cameras from all the new
channels in india and they put it on
on the media on the news 24 by seven
there's a massive protest happening
and then people start believing that the
whole country
is under siege
so that's the kind of narrative the
media creates both sides of the
political divide so
so that's what creates all these
problems in the country
so that's the that's why all of this has
happened you know
okay jaydev says what is the
significance of the falkland islands in
geopolitics what benefits do these
islands provide to the uk and why does
argentina claim them okay where's the
map
where is the map where are the falkland
islands the malvinas
okay
where's the map here's the map
so now we go to the atlantic south
atlantic
so
this here
is south america yes you know that
you come to the southern part
the south eastern part of the south
american continent is argentina
all the way down south to cape horn
cape horn is a very very stormy place
terrible weather terrible weather
so this here is argentina
west of argentina is the country of
chile and east of argentina you have las
islas malvinas
which the british call the falkland
islands okay
now this is occupied by the british by
the uk
now where is the uk if you go all the
way north
here is the uk so this little country
sitting here
occupies these islands
all the way
in the southern hemisphere of the coast
of argentina
and the argent and argentina claims this
island because it is it is like right
right off their coast a couple of
hundred kilometers 300 kilometers maybe
from the coast of argentina it is
natural that if there's this bunch of
islands off the coast of a major country
it should belong to that country
but there's a history behind this the
british occupied the islands for some
time
and there was a war in the 1980s
so what happened is that in 1982 i
believe the argentinians invaded and
occupied these islands
and margaret thatcher
she
ordered her navy her military to launch
an expedition to reconquer the islands
then there was a war over here the
americans kind of supported the uk
and the uk eventually was able to defeat
the argentines and re-establish
re-establish control over these islands
so that's what happened
the capital city is stanley
right
so that's what it is now what benefit
does it provide to either country for
argentina it is
essentially
a matter of honor and prestige that
these islands off our coast should
belong to us very simple why should it
belong to a country that lies a few
several thousand kilometers away
and of course you want more territory if
you hold a bunch of islands it's good
for you
the british
they want
well what geopolitical benefit does the
uk gain from it nothing the uk is not a
world power the uk is a has been power
it is a power that has lost its
relevance and significance in
geopolitics it is no longer a an active
player in geopolitics except as being an
american versailles state
so
it provides no benefits to the uk but it
provides some benefits to the us
because if your vasal state holds some
islands in
this region it's it's good for you you
can use it in the future for some
military purpose or whatever purpose so
that's what it is for the uk it's just
about prestige holding on to to past
glory so they were able to do it in 1982
their military their other navy was
still more powerful than the argentine
navy
and they were tacitly supported by the
us and that's what happened
so uh
so yeah that's that's in very brief
about the falkland islands
and the uk doesn't really have any
major
uh role to play in geopolitics but it's
just holding on to that region for
prestige nothing more
okay what could this be vishal what
could be no could the next major
conflict escalate between greece and
turkey or the aegean islands
would india support greece in such a
situation considering that the turkey
sides with pakistan okay what is this
entire thing about
where's the map we go back to the map
this time we go to the mediterranean
region
so this here is the aegean sea
if you can see my mouse pointer
hopefully you can let me zoom in
in the center of the screen is the
agency
in the west is greece
in the east is turkey anatolia in the
north is
the european
portion of turkey
west of constantinople
which is which was once known as trace
okay so
the agency
is what divides anatolia or turkey from
greece
and if you see there's a whole bunch of
islands there
and
these islands are very close to turkey
but if you see
let's take the island of samos okay
if i click here
it will say that this is part of turkey
so where i clicked
is turkey and just a couple of
kilometers away less than two kilometers
away it is greece
so these greek islands are right off the
coast of turkey a whole bunch of islands
all greek islands right off the coast of
turkey
now obviously turkey covets these
islands turkey is a territorial
territorially expansionist nation
so what happened how did so many greek
islands end up
right off the coast of turkey
to understand that we have to go back to
the 1910s and 1920s
at the end of world war one
the ottoman empire which had
supported germany
and austria-hungary
the ottoman empire
ended up on the losing side
and the victorious powers dismantled the
austro-hungarian empire and the ottoman
empire they carved turkey up into a
bunch of pieces
and
various portions of turkey were handed
over to various european powers
and some parts were in the position of
the
of the balkan states i mean the the
bulgarians had had uh
certain ambitions when it came to
turkish territory the greeks had some
ambitions because originally
the entirety of anatolia was greek
right all of this was originally greek
it was part of the eastern roman empire
which was
which had a immense amount of greek
culture and influence and even before
the roman empire was a thing anatolia
was part of greece the ancient city of
troy
where is it his lake where is it today
uh
somewhere here
it was in anatolia
troy
so the greeks
have territorial ambitions when it comes
to retaking their ancient homeland of
anatolia
so at the end of the second world war
the europeans had taken over turkey now
the turkish nationalist
soldier mustafa kemal
he fought the turkish war of
independence he fought against the
occupying powers he fought against his
own caliph
the last sultan of turkey and he came
out on top he defeated them all he
established an independent nation of
turkey and he was he was given the name
of ataturk by his people the father of
the turks
so when he won the war of independence
all the occupying forces were driven off
and the city of izmir which was known
known as smurna was burned all the
greeks armenians all the christians were
driven off many of them were massacred
and they all escaped from there so the
the turks took over the entirety of uh
of anatolia this peninsular region but
they were not able to take over the
greek islands so the possession of all
these islands remained in the hands of
the greeks in at the end of the turkish
war of independence 1920 22 whatever it
is
and that's where the map has been ever
since but i am sure the turks if they
become militarily more powerful would
want to take over
parts of some of these islands in the
future
we know that they took over cyprus in
the 1970s cyprus is a greek island it
was a greek island until the 1970s which
year was it somewhere in the 70s the
turks invaded cyprus
and they partitioned the country into
two bits into two parts
north cyprus is held by turkey it is
occupied by turkey now
in the south of cyprus is still is still
in greek possession
so they could do this a similar thing in
the future with roads perhaps perhaps
with uh
samos
and there are various other islands like
lesvos and so on
so it could be
it could happen in the future
uh
maybe sometime in the future when things
become more geopolitically fluid
would india support greece in such a
situation considering that turkey sides
with pakistan
you don't support a country out of
principle
you support a country in geopolitics
when you have something to gain
if we support greece over turkey what do
we gain we can issue a statement that we
condemn so and so when we support so and
so but beyond words
india is going to invest nothing in such
a war or such a fight because we don't
quite have a horse in that race
if turkey wins we gain or lose nothing
if greece wins we gain or lose nothing
so from a geopolitical perspective it is
all it has to always be about your own
self-interest your national interest
uh
we would certainly issue a condemnation
to whoever invades first if turkey
invades
any greek island i am sure india would
condemn it and they would vote against
turkey in the u.n so so all of those
symbolic gestures we could do
but beyond that no material support will
be forthcoming for sure unless we have
something to really gain from it so
that's what i can say in brief about
this
joy then says what significance is the
country's name
hold on the global level after turkey
changed its name to turkey
what impact by changing our country's
name to
from republic of bharat to bharatiya
gandhi gandra can create
excuse me
see a name change is a symbolic thing
it has no geopolitical impact as such
it has a symbolic impact it has an
emotional impact
changing a country's name is
aimed at your local people at your local
population it has
implications
at an internal level rather than at an
external level for me i don't care
whether you call turkey turkey or turkey
or ostrich or
whatever
i don't care what you call it it is what
it is
whatever title you put on the
geographical territory it's going to
still behave the same
in geopolitics so from a geopolitical
strategic
geostrategic perspective a name change
does nothing
but from a cultural perspective
it
has a certain significance
so
it's all about the rise of turkish
nationalism we will no longer call uh
define ourselves by a name given to us
by foreigners we will use our own
uh native name for our country that's
the the
that's the message that's been given out
so it's aimed primarily at the people of
turkey that we are going to be a more
nationalist nation now onwards
so if india
changes its name from india to bharat
it is going to mean nothing in
geopolitics but yeah the perception will
change the people of the world will see
india differently uh that yeah india is
becoming more nationalistic there is a
there is a rise of wave of nationalism
and all that that's what the new york
times and the guardian and
washington post etc they will say they
will say it's a continuation of the
nationalistic uh
policies of of the sort of the local of
the government and so on
so there's going to be if we do that it
will have certain some such ripples or
impact but nothing big from a
geopolitical perspective but it will
impact
the self-image
of the people of india
it will
have an effect on the
on the psyche of the people of india
there will be a resurgence of national
pride among the people who are
nationalistic and there will be protests
and riots in our sun and all that from
the people who are within india but they
hate india and who are agents of other
forces so that sort of thing will happen
so that's the whole
basket of scenarios
nikhil says i am a software developer i
use cloud i use cloud hosting uh git
cloud host cloud services like amazon
web services azure ai models other tech
services that are vital to the software
industry on a daily basis there isn't a
single one of them there is an indian
company
i'm afraid of how much power the u.s has
or our entire software industry imagine
if they outlawed
visa and mastercard in russia if they do
the same to in in india with amazon web
services our entire industry will
collapse since we don't have an
alternative what are your views on this
i agree with you completely
cloud hosting is an integral part
of
the entire software industry
if they cut off access to aws or or any
other cloud hosting service or to the
major cloud hosting services
the entire sector could collapse
the entire iit sector software sector
could collapse
uh get all of these things are based in
the u.s i spoke about web web 3 is that
in
web 2 and web 3 and web 5. web 3 is
about the decentralized web but nobody
owns the information where all the
information is available in a
decentralized manner that needs to be
implemented right now too much power
resides in the hands of one country in
us in a small number of individuals
within that one country a bunch of
billionaires
from silicon valley
and the people who who own those
billionaires which is the the us deep
state
so it is extremely dangerous for the
world because so much power resides in
such a small number of people and they
can cut it off at will they can deny it
to you at will
if you don't uh
bend
to their their demands
so we have to understand that this is
what we are living through right now
our country
is technically independent but we are
still so very dependent on
on the west on the us for all of these
things
they
they switched off mastercard and visa
in russia they cut off
access to swift and it's is it's caused
so much uh trouble in russia
now we have developed upi
we are developing the next generation
the next level of upi
and
so that's great
the indian payments infrastructure is
way better way more advanced and way
faster than what they have in the west
so that is an advantage we have created
now we need to start developing our own
infrastructure whether it is cloud
hosting or any of these other services
all of that needs to be replicated in
india and hopefully
we will see the rise of blockchain the
rise of web 3 and hopefully something
beyond web 3 web 4 web 5 whatever you
want to call it which is truly
decentralized a truly decentralized
internet so that nobody actually can cut
off access to anything
we have had this since the for the past
20 years or so the p2p technology what's
it called um
torrent torrent technology bittorrent
and all that
so that is something those of those
files can never be taken of the internet
as long as somebody is seeding them
it's all available in a decentralized
manner no you can see you simply cannot
delete that from the internet once once
it's there it's there so if
the entire web is decentralized like
that using blockchain technology then
these problems will go over but even
today web 3 even web 3 is not fully
decentralized it is still
very much
in the custody of a small number of
people in silicon valley so the internet
needs to evolve it needs to become
properly truly genuinely decentralized
and india should also while that all
while that happens india should in
parallel at the same time create its own
infrastructure
which which replicates whatever the us
has cloud services ai models
get
and so on aws azure or whatever all of
that needs to happen in india also so
that we can fully truly become
independent right now we are dependent
on the us for all of these things so
this is a very good point that nikki
makes and i agree with him
kieran says why has communism never been
implemented the way karl marx intended
it to be he predicted capitalism will
collapse and naturally transition to a
socialism based to socialism will that
ever be possible
so the question really is
why has communism
never been implemented the way karl marx
wanted it to be implemented
okay
so my question is
what did karl marx want
how did he want
communism
to be implemented
how
what he said is
society is controlled by the capitalists
they control the needs of means of
production they control the means of
distribution they have a stranglehold a
chokehold of the economy
and everything else they
own the people who are in power and blah
blah all that he said society is
terrible it's very
unequal
the proletariat
the the unwashed masses the laborers
they are oppressed
so what karl marx said is that there
needs to be
a dictatorship of the proletariat
a number of people a group of people who
will hold all power
in the name of the proliterate of the
workers workers of the world unite unite
together or through the capitalists
overthrow the bourgeoisie get rid of the
of the
of the lumpan elements or whatever it is
the lumpan proletariat
so the proletariat must rise up there
needs to be a revolution
karl marx wanted a revolution and he
wanted a dictatorship of the predator
yet and he wanted collectivized a
collectivized society where all property
is collectivized nobody owns anything
but everybody owns everything
you don't own anything in specific but
you own everything everybody is given
whatever they need
right but you have to work in exchange
for that and everybody lives an ideal
life
work in the daytime read in the evening
criticizing the night drink a glass of
whiskey and go to sleep that sort of
thing so the ideal marxist life that's
what he wanted
so
what are the specifics he said that the
way to
transition
from a capitalist society to a marxist
society is via a people's revolution
so he wanted the transition to be via
revolutions a revolution is
a violent overthrow of the existing
government existing regime so he wanted
violence
did he specify
what sort of people should lead the the
revolution
what sort of leadership did he envisage
that would lead the revolution he said
nothing about that
and when we talk about violence it's
always the most violent
people who become the leaders at the end
of a violent coup
typically
secondly
he said there should be a dictatorship
of the proletariat
did he ever say that what kind of people
should come to power in this
dictatorship of the proletariat and who
will decide who comes to power and who
and who will lead
a
post-capitalist society
in a pro once marxism is established who
should lead the people who should be in
the government
he never said anything about that
he never defined the ideal leadership he
never defined the leadership structure
he never defined how the leadership will
be selected or elected will there be a
democratic election or did he despise
democracy did he want
authoritarian rule he said nothing about
these things
and that is why capitalism
communism has never been implemented in
in any any proper way because karl marx
never defined what he really wanted he
said violent overthrow of capitalism and
dictatorship
you could interpret that in 3000 million
different ways
so he has deliberately created this
problem
and every every time communism fails
they say that yeah you know they did not
implement it properly there is no right
way or proper way of implementing it
because karl marx never defined what the
correct way is
communism
marxism invariably attracts the most
despotic people
because the people who truly understand
what marxism is
well they they are the ones who are the
most ambitious and the most unscrupulous
people
so that is why marxism or communism has
always failed it has always caused
misery trouble
and uh
and the starvation genocide
massacres and so on look at
uh look at russia look at the ussr look
at look at the communist china look at
mao's regime look at
stalin's regime nikita khrushchev and
all that
the gulags
look at uh polpot's experiment in
cambodia
look at
angola look at all the other marxist
experiments it's always been a disaster
at the end right
i'm not saying it's it's a bad idea
if you could have
you know there are certain indians who
say there should be dharmic marxism well
maybe that should be that should be
tried
i'm just
saying you know
so there are a million different ways of
interpreting marxism and implementing it
thus far it's been done in a terrible
way maybe there could be a good way of
doing it but we still haven't found it i
mean we still haven't seen it
implemented in a way that is actually
beneficial in the long run for the
people and the nation
all right
okay
jaydev says what kind of politics is
going to be played in space race in the
space race and mars colonization who
will dominate this arena the powerful
people or the one who reaches first
so the the the easiest way to understand
this is to draw a parallel with the age
of uh
the past 500 years
the age of exploration of the seas
so the european powers
uh
they developed a means of navigation
ships
the compass the sextant and various
instruments and so on and they were able
to map out the trade routes the various
sea routes and all they were they
started exploring the oceans
and the portuguese did that the spanish
did that the british did that the french
did that all the major european powers
were on this race
to explore the world to explore the far
reaches of all the oceans the south
atlantic north and last atlantic north
pacific south south pacific antarctic
ocean the arctic ocean and rediscover
india rediscover china and so on and so
forth they discovered the americas
there was a big race
to discover new places to map out the
entire world and to colonize every last
piece or last square kilometer
of the non-european land mass
right
so the same thing is eventually going to
happen in space
we are at the very beginning
very beginning of the space race
and in the 21st century the two or three
nations that will lead the world in
space exploration are the two or three
countries that will lead that will rule
the world overall
it's not going to be more than two or
three countries eventually there'll be
just one i believe
right one or two maximum two
so
who will dominate this arena the most
powerful power or the one that reaches
first
i think it could be the one who reaches
eventually
you don't need to have first mover
advantage if you look at technology if
you look at exploration
colonization the one who moved first is
not necessarily the one who succeeded
overall
who came first to india
it was a portuguese
but eventually in the british came a
century later
the british came very late by a hundred
years
and yet they were the ones who conquered
india eventually
and they established the largest
empire the world has ever seen until the
u.s empire
so um it's not always
the most powerful
one that starts
so as of today the us is the most
powerful
um the chinese are number two so these
are the number two nations the top two
nations are these two gonna be the one
that dominates space in the future in
the next 100 200 500 years maybe not
they will certainly be the two three
countries that move the first move the
fastest
um
but eventually the ones that
achieve the biggest technological
breakthroughs
and do the most with the least they
could be the ones who dominate in the
long run
so
space exploration is going to tie into
the geopolitics that we have on earth
because space exploration is all about
resources it's all about expanding to
new territories it's about acquiring new
territories new resources new lands
and
so that's all about
control it's all about power it's all
about wealth
uh so in the moon there is this rush
right now going on the the great moon
rush is happening now
uh the americans want to go there the
chinese want to go there india possibly
hopefully will not be left behind
so in the long run you will see colonies
on the moon in the long run you will see
colonies on mars
the first colonies could be american
russian chinese colonies perhaps
but who will dominate in the end
it depends we don't know quite yet
but the ones that will
uh make the most technological progress
eventually will win
so that's what will happen in the long
run
dengar sinchowan says we humans are very
weak compared to some giant reptiles yet
we survived
so if our weak selves made it then why
couldn't a massive prehistoric alpha
predator like titanobua
was able to ensure his survival
okay
so we humans are tiny and weak compared
to other animals
we survived
other animals are way more powerful than
us even our cousins the chimpanzees the
orangutans the gorillas who are so close
to us genetically they are much more
powerful physically than us right
and the massive animals used to used to
exist the titan of war so who is this
guy titan aboard it was the largest
snake that ever lived let me show you
what this creature looked like
titanoboa let's go to google for a
change
where is google
and let's search for titan award
t-i-t-a-n-o-b-o-a
b-o-a
titan of a snake so this snake lived
about 60-65 million years before today
it has gone extinct of course
um
it lived right after the the
extinction event of the non-avian
dinosaurs massive massive snake
let's see a comparison so see how big it
was way way huger than a human being
massive snake
king of the snakes the largest snake
that we know of
that's how large this creature was
much much larger than the largest snake
that lives today which is the anaconda
so the size is about 43 feet
longer than a bus and it could easily
eat several human human beings if if it
wanted to so why did such a powerful
massive
monstrous snake
die out and why did us little humans
survive that is the question
so
size
can be a disadvantage
from an evolutionary perspective when we
talk about evolution we're talking about
the
the course that a species takes over
millions of years
okay
so there is something called
evolutionary advantage survival of the
fittest you don't need to be enormous
and muscular to be fit
sometimes you can be thin and weak
physically but be fitter so if we look
at the entire history in the entire
known history of our planet of the life
on our planet
then from all the life forms that we
know of from the fossil record etc
the most dangerous species that has ever
lived
the deadliest species
that has ever lived
is homo sapiens
not the dinosaurs not t-rex
not titan or not anybody not any other
species that most dangerous
predator
that has ever existed is homo sapiens
and
the tool that we
have used is not our massive strength
or or anything that anything like that
it's the brain it's the brain power we
are the most intelligent
of the species that that we have known
to have existed on the planet
and that intelligence is the greatest
tool that we have it is the greatest
advantage that we have and we are
naturally
violent species we are a war-like
species we our entire history is a
history of warfare
the entire history of the human species
is a history of warfare even our close
cousins the chimpanzees are just as
aggressive and violent as us they have
clan warfare and gang warfare you should
see the documentaries brutal
so it is something that's in our dna we
are
the most intelligent species that
possibly ever lived on our planet and we
are extremely aggressive extremely
violent
that's in our dna
so that is why we have been able to rise
to the top of the food chain today all
other species are subsidiary to us we
are on top of the fruit food chain we
are the apex predator we are a super
predator
right
even if t-rex was alive today
i think people would be barbecuing the
t-rex and they would fight t-rex uh
meat in the supermarkets
the size doesn't matter
a t-rex is nothing compared to compared
to a
10-year-old child with a with a gun
right
so
and and sometimes a large size can be a
massive evolutionary disadvantage if you
are a 50-foot snake imagine how much
food you need to eat on a on a daily or
weekly basis
these giant reptiles snakes pythons
anacondas they typically eat food once
a week or two
to three times a month
but they need to eat large amounts of
food in order to sustain their bodies
because they have very massive bodies
and these are
predators carnivorous animals so a
massive snake like titanoboar would have
to have to have to hunt regularly and
eat massive amounts of food
and this was primarily a snake that
lived in the in the waters
and it it hunted on sea animals fish
mammals etc
etc
and in case there is climate change or
some kind of evolutionary change in
which the food becomes scarce then a
massive species like this will easily go
extinct
because it won't be able to find some
food to ensure its long-term survival
whereas if you are a small species
you don't need that much food and if you
are intelligent enough you can find food
from anywhere in any way possible
using foraging techniques using hunting
hunter gatherer techniques or if you
invented agriculture so that is why we
survived and these species like titan
above etcetera went extinct we were
around when the dinosaur extinction
happened
when the chick shalom impact event
happened 66 million years ago when all
the non-avian dinosaurs died out our
ancestors were there and they survived
somehow
so we are a very
hardy species and our ancestors at that
time 66 million years ago did not look
like us they were this small they were
rat like animals
right that's what they were small tiny
mammals that lived under the ground they
behaved like rats
and their descendants ended up like us
so survival of the species is a
long-term game it's something that
happens over millions of years and if
you evolve in the right way you will
rise to the top of the food chain as we
have
and these massive beasts that look so
impressive they don't last long
unfortunately
that is the story
okay
are motivational speakers and life
coaches any good can they make some
difference in the lives of their
audience
um
you know motivation is for is for
beginners
if you need motivation to start
you will get you will end up nowhere
motivation should not come from outside
you motivation should come from inside
you and motivation will come if you know
who you are and what your path should be
if you have a long-term goal
that is worthwhile that is worth
achieving then you don't need external
motivation your motivation will come
from itself you will wake up in the
morning ready to go and fight
to achieve that goal in 10 years time
these motivational speakers what they do
is they play on your emotions they try
to charge you up
so it gives you an emotional high yeah
i'm gonna do it blah blah blah after
half an hour that emotion is gone the
motivation is also gone so
what motivational speakers do is they
conflate emotions with motivation
emotions are things that go up and down
up and down a person who's driven by
emotions will never achieve much in
their life emotional people
are like a boat or like boats in the sea
when there's a big wave they go up when
the wave when there are no waves
it will be completely flat you go up and
down on the emotional roller coaster and
you don't have a stable life
so motivational speakers try to play on
your emotions but after half an hour the
motivation is gone because the emotion
is gone
true motivation comes from inside
and if you have motivation you don't
need any motivational speaker or any
motivational music or anything you just
wake up ready to fight and and go on the
mission
so
to make a difference in your life you
need to have a goal a big goal a 10-year
goal
and then you can
then that will motivate you
uh life coaches are a different breed of
animal
they a life coach i imagine would give
you strategies and tactics
about how to achieve a goal so let's
explain how it what it is like
let's say you are
at point a and you want to end up at
point
d
from a to d
and you don't know how to get there you
don't have the map
let's say you are sitting in in
bangalore and you want to reach
berlin
you know i am you are here and you want
to reach there but you don't have a map
so you don't know how to go there
should i go by train should i go by taxi
should i go by auto record should i go a
plane should i go by submarine how
should i go
and what route to take
so you need a map so what a life coach a
good life coach would do is they will
give you a map and they will show you
two three different ways of reaching
there and they will also show you the
best way of reaching there
so that's what a life coach does a life
coach is very different from a
motivational speaker life coach if you
have a good one i expect would make a
good difference in your life but
motivation speakers are just ah they
just play on people's emotions i uh
i i don't see any value in that
personally maybe it helps some people if
it does help you good for you
it's never helped me i've seen some
motivational speeches which isn't all
you know it's it's just
they're just playing on people's
emotions
right so that's what i have to say about
this
an amazing indian citizen says have you
ever felt that you have have you ever
felt that you have learned everything in
science history geopolitics etc if yes
how did you overcome it i have never had
to overcome this because i've never felt
this way
i always feel that i know nothing i i
have so much to learn
i am simply sharing with you all what i
am learning i always read i am always
learning something every day there is so
much i have to learn
i know so little whether it is science
or its mathematics or history or
geopolitics there is so much history
that i still haven't explored that i
would like to explore there are so many
my new details that are very interesting
about various phases of indian and world
history especially world history there
is so much in science that i haven't
explored
there is so much mathematics i still
need to learn
probably i won't learn that because it's
kind of a i only learn certain math if
it's useful if it has some useful
application in in physics but that's how
it is so i have never felt once in my
life once even once that i know
everything
the
the constant feeling i have always had
is that i have so much to learn i have
learned nothing thus far
and that's why i i always keep learning
something
so that's my perspective that's how i am
i have never ever for one micro second
had the feeling that i know so much no
man i don't
right okay
that's it for today's uh
questions let's take some live chat
questions
for the next five minutes
i and when i talk about motivational
speakers i
i am not pointing fingers individually
at anybody i don't even know who the big
motivational speakers out there are okay
because i don't i don't consume that
sort of content i don't watch that i'm
not into that
so please don't uh construe this as me
pointing figures at anybody i'm not i'm
not i'm sure there must be some good
ones that also
out there
so yeah that's what i have to say about
this matter now any questions um
please answer mukhabhadya's
what is that question
okay look there are millions of
questions here but uh
if i can find
so
some people get really upset that i did
not pick their question please please my
dear friends please understand i get
thousands of questions every week in the
comments i can only pick 20 30.
and in the chat here i can see questions
coming in every second i
most likely am going to miss your
question i try my best to break up the
questions so please don't take it
personally if i don't answer your
question
i am trying to pick up the questions
that will serve everybody as best as
possible that will help the maximum
number of people
all right so please don't take it
personally now let's see some questions
if there are any
other says how to learn geopolitics just
like just like me and how to read book
properly if you just like you remember
the book pro the whole book properly how
to learn geopolitics i have never
learned geopolitics i have learned
history i have been incredibly curious
about history i started with world
history i've read
i have spent thousands of hours possibly
reading history books
okay world history egyptian history
roman history greek history
indian history eventually chinese
history mongol history japanese history
history from the colonial era and so on
i have spent thousands of hours i've
read thousands of books thousands of
articles you cannot understand
geopolitics
unless you understand history well
and you cannot understand history well
unless you spend thousands of hours
reading thousands of books there is no
substitute for hard work people i'm not
saying you are making doing this but i
see this question lots of times and
people
seek shortcuts give me one book if i
read that book i will know geopolitics
never gonna happen
there is no substitute for hard work
there is no substitute for patience
okay
so you got to put in the time you got to
read the best way to learn geopolitics
is to be incredibly curious about
history world history and the more you
read about world history the more you
read the more you'll be able to
cross link
events across the world and the patterns
will slowly start becoming visible and
once the patterns of history start
becoming visible you will start
understanding the cause and effect
dynamic and once you understand the
cause and effect chain the causality
chain
that's when you will start understanding
geopolitics because the same patterns
are seeing are visible today these are
timeless patterns
and all the events and forces and powers
that drew in persons that drove
historical events in the past centuries
the same patterns are applicable today
we are still seeing the same patterns
today you understand history you
understand geopolitics and you will
understand the root causes of all the
conflicts that are happening today
there is no substitute for hard work
there is no substitute for reading
thousands of books and there is no
substitute for having patience so i
don't have any shortcuts to offer to any
of you but i can offer you the path the
only path i know
all right
hope that helps
okay let me take maybe
a question or two more
um
uh when will you do a one-on-one video
conference i love asking questions in
purple person you know i i kind of
enjoyed that but i also that that format
i have tried multiple times in the past
the problem in that format is that
people kind of take advantage of me
being a nice person i don't i'm not rude
i'm not i'm not a root person
i
i'm a very lenient person and people
the one rule i have on these shows when
i do a video thing is that everybody
asks one question but then people take
advantage and they ask multiple
questions they want to hog the thing
they want to hold on to the thing as
long as possible and
so the i personally feel that when i do
this video calls when i invite people to
talk to me on video and ask questions on
video there is no quality control
anybody can come and ask anything which
is not a big problem but sometimes the
question they ask is not the best
question
and sometimes they just try to prolong
their time on screen as long as possible
so it's not beneficial
to everybody it's beneficial to one
person at a time
the intent of this show is to answer the
best possible questions from this whole
pool that i get every week and help as
many people as possible with some
knowledge that i may have
that is the intent of this show the show
is not about me it's not about any
individual person it's about everybody
as a whole
that's what i wish to do and that's why
i have kind of stopped the video thing
video conference thing
right now maybe i will not do that in
the
i have no immediate plans of restarting
that
so yeah
it's it's i'm sure people enjoy it i
also enjoy it but it's not beneficial
for for everybody so that's why i am not
doing it right now
okay
uh any other questions so many questions
uh
i will take one more final
question
okay shri answers where what do people
who live in china or japan think where
does buddhism come from everyone knows
it comes from india
no question everyone knows it
the chinese know it comes from india the
japanese know it comes from india
everybody who is a buddhist knows where
it comes from
so there is no doubt about that and over
there they don't even see much of a
difference between buddhism hinduism
it's it's
it's only us in india who try to because
of political reasons who are trying to
create a
delineation or dividing line between
both the dharma and hindu dharma and
their separate things no there is no
such thing as a separate thing they are
the same thing
there are small technical differences
between buddhism and hinduism
but look at the life look at the morals
and ethics that the people who follow
buddhism or hinduism exactly the same
the same values the same morality the
same ethics the same principles yeah
some technical differences about whether
there is a soul or not or whether the
soul is immortal or not those technical
differences don't matter
your
values are the same
your lifestyle is the same
so it's the same thing be
the difference is maybe one percent
the similarities are 99 percent if you
don't believe me see what the dalai lama
says the dalai lama is the highest
ranking buddhist uh person today
see what the dalai lama has said
multiple times
about buddhism and hinduism if you don't
trust me
i'm sure you can trust the dalai lama
the greatest authority on buddhism today
so that's what i have to say about this
and with this we come to the end of
today's session thank you very much
everybody as always a great pleasure
answering all these questions
and i can see new people are coming in
with some new questions which is great
to see so we shall continue doing this
and i will see you in the next episode
next week until then take care thank you
very much great again to be with you all
and i will see you next week
take care
bye